<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to peace A funeral sermon on Job 22.21. Preached upon the decease of the right honourable Elizabeth, Countess of Ranalagh. By Daniel Burgess.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834686</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1808:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to peace A funeral sermon on Job 22.21. Preached upon the decease of the right honourable Elizabeth, Countess of Ranalagh. By Daniel Burgess.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Jonathan Robinson, in St. Paul's Church-Yard, and Brab. Ailmer in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ranelagh, Elizabeth Jones, --  Countess of, d. 1695 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XXII, 21 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39190:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Way to Peace.</p>
            <p>A FUNERAL SERMON On <hi>Job</hi> 22.21.</p>
            <p>Preached upon the Deceaſe Of the Right Honourable ELIZABETH, Counteſs of <hi>Ranalagh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>DANIEL BURGESS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and <hi>Brab. Ailmer</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1695.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39190:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39190:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39190:3"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:39190:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable RICHARD Earl of <hi>Ranalagh,</hi> And to his moſt Vertuous Daughters, ELIZABETH Counteſs of <hi>Kildare,</hi> Lady FRANCEL, and Lady KATHERINE <hi>Jones.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord, and Ladies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have performed this ſmall Service, to the Memory of one deſerving <hi>to be had in everlaſting Remembrance!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Part</hi> of it which concerns her Heavenly Vertues, claimeth as its undoubted Right, and is ſure to have, your moſt honourable Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Although the <hi>whole</hi> be ſo blemiſh'd with the Author's Imperfections, that it deſerveth his Bluſh, and needeth your Pardon!</p>
            <p>A Pardon, whereof he deſpairs not; becauſe, <hi>through your overflowing Affection unto the Deceaſed,</hi> You have pleaſed to honour me with many great Favours. And becauſe, as every one ſeeth, <hi>the Greateſt and the Beſt Perſons be not the hardeſt to pleaſe!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Gratitude ſhall ever keep my Prayer aſcending to the Almighty, for <hi>your noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily!</hi>
               <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:39190:4"/>Whereof, ſo renowned Relatives, as <hi>your Lordſhip's incomparable Mother,</hi> the Illuſtrious <hi>Roger</hi> Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Mr. <hi>Robert Boil,</hi> have long ago obliged me to be a true Votary!</p>
            <p>May your Redeemer's Grace hold you ſafe upon <hi>the Precipices of your Proſperity!</hi> And make your ſecular Grandeurs to become Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his <hi>preſent Favour,</hi> and Pledges of your <hi>future Felicity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May your <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> be Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to this World! And when you are Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the next, <hi>May</hi> you carry the Peace of God with you, and leave the Praiſe of Men behind you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thus prayeth</hi> Your Honours moſt Obliged, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>DANIEL BURGESS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39190:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON preach'd upon the Deceaſe of the right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Ranalagh.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Job 22.21.</bibl> Acquaint now thy ſelf with Him, and be at Peace, thereby Good ſhall come unto thee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Lion hath rored, who will not Fear?</hi> Death hath, this Year, bin indeed the <hi>King of Terrors.</hi> And, we are deaf unto Thunder, if, yet, we do not <hi>Hear and Fear.</hi> The <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of the Earth,</hi> it hath taken from this Earth! Yea, the Mighty <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and glorious <hi>Ornaments</hi> of our Weal. Open your Volumes, O ye antient Records! and name us, if ye can, ſuch a <hi>MARY</hi> as this Kingdom and World hath loſt in this Year; Such a <hi>Cedar,</hi> ſuch an <hi>Olive,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Vine,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:39190:5"/>ſuch a Guardian-Angel! Bleſſed be the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Mercies; he hath continued to us the <hi>nurſing Father of our Country!</hi> But of what a <hi>Mother</hi> hath he bereaved it? You have heard, and joined (I hope) in the National Groans, ſuch as ſpake Church and State to be half-expiring. You have ſeen the whole Realm turn'd into a Houſe of Mourning! And now,</p>
            <p>I need not tell you, <hi>the Lion ſtill rores!</hi> Our offended God hath not yet done with us. No, but is ſtill <hi>Writing bitter things</hi> againſt us; and hath <hi>ſtained the Glory of this Month</hi> with additional Darkneſs. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved another <hi>burning and ſhining Light</hi> of our World; another rare Exemplar of Chriſtian Piety. You do know what a Princeſs thereof is fallen; for, you know the Lady <hi>RANALAGH</hi> is deceaſed.</p>
            <p>My buſineſs hereon, is not to ſound an <hi>Encomium,</hi> but preach a <hi>Sermon.</hi> For, we need to be Inſtructed, ſhe needs not be Praiſed. It is well enough known, how nearly <hi>Diamonds</hi> do imitate the Stars of Heaven; how far <hi>the Moon</hi> out-ſhineth the Lamps which ſurround her; and how vaſtly <hi>this Elect Lady</hi> did excel the Commoners of the Houſhold of Faith!</p>
            <p>It is true, an <hi>utter Silence</hi> of her Sanctity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39190:5"/>would be <hi>Sacrilege.</hi> To bury ſo much of Heaven in dark Oblivion, would together rob <hi>God</hi> of Praiſe, and his <hi>Church</hi> of Profit. Yea, the <hi>World</hi> of a due Debt. For, Saints <hi>Examples</hi> be their <hi>Legacies</hi> to the whole World; and, when they are by any means detained, it is no leſs a Number that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded of ſo rich a Treaſure. Wherefore, (as a more <hi>compleat Memorial</hi> of this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<note place="margin">From Mr. <hi>J. J.</hi> her Reverend Paſtor.</note> is expected from the fitteſt Hand) there ſhall not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what will be of ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in this Sermon.</p>
            <p>This, whoſe Theme is the Text, which ſhe <hi>bound about her Neck, wrote on the Table of her Heart; held faſt, and kept as her Life.</hi> As that, which, <hi>when ſhe Walked, did Lead her: when ſhe Slept, did Keep her; when ſhe Awaked, did Talk with her.</hi> The Text, which ſhe thought eminently-apt to <hi>give Subtility to the moſt Simple; and, to the moſt Indocile, both Knowledg and Diſcretion.</hi> The Text, which I have hoped (through the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt) to find ſuch at this time.</p>
            <p>Inaſmuch as it preſents, both the <hi>Whole Counſel of God unto us;</hi> and, our <hi>Whole Encouragement from God to follow</hi> it!</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:39190:6"/>
            <p>The Counſel, is One and All; to <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint our ſelves with God.</hi> And the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement is no leſs; <hi>Peace and all Good from Him.</hi> Familiarly, the Hebrews do ſpeak Imperatively, when they mean Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely; <hi>Be at Peace,</hi> is as much as, <hi>Thou ſhalt be at Peace.</hi> And, an Indefinit <hi>(in re neceſſariâ)</hi> is an Univerſal; <hi>Good ſhall come unto thee,</hi> is plainly, <hi>All Good ſhall come unto thee!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Particulars, run, without more ado, into this Poſition: <hi>Acquaintance with God is the way to Peace and all Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Inclination</hi> unto Peace and Good, is as univerſal as our Nature. And, ſo is the <hi>Capacity</hi> of it; for, unto All that will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it on his Terms, it is offered by God's Grace. <hi>His Offer</hi> is unqueſtionably ſincere; and no Man is Miſerable, but by the Fault of his own Will. Never periſhed any Adult Reprobate, but by being Obſtinate. And, as to <hi>Man's Deſire,</hi> it is moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently Eager; witneſs, its Purſuits of all imaginary Good; and its Flights from all apprehended Oppoſites. It is not, as the Sand of <hi>Africa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Feritas calet: <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</hi>
               </note> Cold and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren; but, as it's ſaid of <hi>Scythia,</hi> tho all things, beſide, be fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen to Death; yet the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39190:6"/>therein, is hot as Fire. So muſt we ſay of Lapſed and unrenewed Man: his <hi>Luſt</hi> after Happineſs is ſtill moſt Flagrant, though all right <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> of its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of the way to attain it, and of the Neceſſity of attending to the Divine Oracles to learn both, be utterly Extinct.</p>
            <p>By means hereof, <hi>the many</hi> (and, <hi>next to All</hi>) do ſeek Peace where it is not to be found. Grope for it in the <hi>furrows of the Field,</hi> hunt for it in <hi>Parks,</hi> trade for it in <hi>Ships,</hi> flatter for it in <hi>Courts,</hi> fight for it in <hi>Battels.</hi> Not averted from the Folly of their Toils, by the Fruſtration of their Hopes; while the Earth ſaith of Happineſs, <hi>It is not in me;</hi> the Sea ſaith, <hi>It is not in me;</hi> and imperial Crowns do ſay as demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <hi>We have not the Gem you look for!</hi> But, as more <hi>ſilly Birds</hi> than the Hiſtorians, they continue to flock unto the <hi>Painted Grapes.</hi> And, as under Inchantment, keep flying at Impoſſibilities, without ſhame of Diſappointment.</p>
            <p>The Truth I have propoſed, is Divine Eye-ſalve. Which, if the good Spirit do ſet in with it, will enlighten our <hi>Minds;</hi> and give us to ſee better things. Even with a Sight which ſhall raviſh our <hi>Hearts,</hi> into a full, free, and firm <hi>Choice,</hi> and <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:39190:7"/>of them. In order to this, be it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively conſidered what is the <hi>Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of God,</hi> and what the <hi>Peace and Good which infallibly follows it.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1. Of <hi>Acquaintance with God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A comprehenſive Duty, the <hi>whole Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> of Religion! A ſhort <hi>Map</hi> whereof, followeth in theſe Poſitions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God conſiſteth in theſe Particulars,</hi> viz. (1.) <hi>Knowledg of Him;</hi> of Him and of his Will, as revealed in his Word. As many as are acquainted with Him, muſt <hi>know him from the leaſt to the greateſt,</hi> Jer. 31.33. Ignorance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly alienates; for, both <hi>in Nature and Grace, the Mind goes before the Will;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can this <hi>Chuſe,</hi> more than that <hi>Knows. Qi non Sentit, non Conſentit, Jeti.</hi> Hence is, the <hi>Inchoation</hi> of this Acquaintance ſaid to be made, by the opening of our Eyes or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. The <hi>Increaſe</hi> of it, to be made by Knowledg, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. And the <hi>Perfection</hi> of it in Heaven, to be made by ſeeing God as He is, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. Such an ingredient of Acquaintance, is Knowledg. I mean, <hi>Natural</hi> Knowledg, corrected and enlarged by <hi>Scriptural;</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39190:7"/>both refined and raiſed by <hi>Spiritual.</hi> Bats, are not Saints; and Moles, are none of God's Friends. But, without <hi>the Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation</hi> giving clearneſs and ſweetneſs unto their Knowledg, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Doctors and Sophi's are no more; <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing as they ought to know.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Reverence of Him,</hi> is alſo in this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. By this Reverence, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not that Fear, which is the Baſtard of Error; and ſprings from a conceit that the ſupream King is a Tyrant. Void of <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> tho full of <hi>Power; Almighty,</hi> but not <hi>moſt Merciful.</hi> A Fear, which <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemes God,</hi> and <hi>tormenteth Man;</hi> draws God in the frightful <hi>Picture,</hi> and puts Man into the diſtracting <hi>Terror,</hi> of the Devil. Reverence, is the <hi>mixt Affection of Love and Fear;</hi> riſing from perſwaſion of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Power. Maintained by this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, that its Object is as <hi>gracious as great.</hi> One which together magnifies the Lord, and regulates his Servants. Sheweth his Majeſty to be <hi>Serene,</hi> as well as <hi>Dread;</hi> and maketh his Subjects both <hi>Confident</hi> and <hi>Humble:</hi> That is, as Holy Angels be, moſt <hi>governable,</hi> and not at all <hi>ſervile.</hi> For, their Fulneſs of Joy is not abated, by the Reverence which compoſes them for Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39190:8"/>The <hi>Covering of their Faces,</hi> doth not in the leaſt prejudice their <hi>Beatific Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Now ſo eſſential is this Reverence unto Acquaintance with God, that <hi>Pagan Moraliſts</hi> could not but ſee it in their Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. With them, <hi>all Religion</hi> was ſtiled <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence;</hi> and all who followed it,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> were named <hi>Men of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> The divinely inſpired Writers are in nothing more expreſs. The God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is called the <hi>Fear or Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of</hi> Iſrael, Gen. 31.42. And, <hi>He that ought to be feared,</hi> Pſal. 75.11. His Fear and Reverence, is alſo ſaid to be our <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> Job 28.28. The <hi>Beginning,</hi> or (as that Text rather ſpeaks) the <hi>Principal</hi> Part of it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſtal. Ainſw. Hammond,</hi> in Loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. Inſomuch that it is beyond all peradventure; they who know not the Divine Goodneſs, ſo as to fear its Forfeiture; and know not his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo as to fear the Frowns of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; they are <hi>alienated,</hi> and <hi>Enemies in their Minds!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) <hi>Love of Him.</hi> Love that conſiſts of <hi>Eſtimation</hi> and <hi>Choice.</hi> Our <hi>Valuation</hi> of his <hi>Excellencies,</hi> and our <hi>Option</hi> of him for them. Then we love God, when our <hi>Judgments</hi> determine Him to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39190:8"/>Object of our Happineſs; and our <hi>Hearts,</hi> renouncing all Competitors, do em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Him as ſuch. Conſtancy is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood in both; and ſo is Tranſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>Conſtancy;</hi> becauſe, a tranſient <hi>Paſſion</hi> of Love, without the firm and fixed <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> of it, is unworthy of the Name of Love. Should a Man, for a Fit, equal the moſt paſſionate Love of the Holy Martyrs; if, by and by, his Eſteem and Choice of God do expire, he is to be numbred among thoſe who have not the true Love of God in them. Again, <hi>Tranſcendency;</hi> becauſe (there being no compare between Finite and Infinite;) if the conſtant Torrent of our Love toward God ſho'd riſe no higher than it doth toward Creatures; it might be truly ſaid, that <hi>our Love were Hatred:</hi> and no <hi>Honour,</hi> but high <hi>Contempt</hi> of Him. For, among the Worms of this Earth, he is held to hate his <hi>Father,</hi> who loves him but as much as he loves his <hi>Hawk,</hi> or his <hi>Hound.</hi> And, extremely to deſpiſe his <hi>King,</hi> who makes him but equal to his <hi>Footman.</hi> In ſhort; there is no Medium betwixt ſo loving God, and hating of Him. <hi>He that is not</hi> thus tranſcendently and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly <hi>for God, he is againſt Him,</hi> Luke 11.23. And, he that is againſt Him, is ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39190:9"/>unacquainted with Him. Becauſe, it's a <hi>Natural Principle,</hi> as well as a <hi>Moral Duty,</hi> to love God when we know Him. Nor <hi>can</hi> we do otherwiſe, if we take him for the true and ſole Object of our Rational Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite! No; but we muſt as neceſſarily reject Idols, and love God, as a ſenſible hungry Man caſts away <hi>Stones,</hi> and eateth <hi>Bread.</hi> The beloved Diſciple ſaith as much as this; <hi>He that loveth not, knoweth not God! hath not ſeen Him, neither known Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">(4.) <hi>Converſe with Him,</hi> is likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in this Acquaintance. <hi>Can two walk together, except they be agreed?</hi> or will they be agreed, and not walk together? Who did ever conceive of Acquaintance, without Fellowſhip and Communion? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, profane Wits laugh to ſcorn the Phraſe of <hi>Communion with God;</hi> conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that, all who profeſs to enjoy it, do embrace but a Shadow, and hug no more than an empty Cloud. And more than a few, who are bleſt with the Fruition of it, are not well able to expreſs or form diſtinct Conceptions of it. But it muſt be ſaid, that to queſtion whether there be ſuch a thing or no, is to queſtion whether there be any ſuch thing as <hi>Acquaintance with God,</hi> or any <hi>Religion?</hi> Yet it may not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39190:9"/>be denied, but that there have been Brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Creatures, who by their ſwelling Words of Vanity and of Blaſphemy, have rendred this Phraſe obnoxious to Scorn and Calumny. I ſhall here endeavour to give ſuch a Notion of it, as ſhall not fear Obloquy, or give Occaſion for it. By Converſe with God, and Communion, I underſtand Sacred Diſcourſe. Holy Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues, between God and the <hi>Enochs,</hi> who humbly walk with Him. God ſpeaking to them, by Excitations of Grace and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections of Heavenly Thoughts; they ſpeaking unto God, by gracious Deſires and ſolemn Addreſſes. God ſpeaking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>Words of Inſtruction</hi> directing them unto Duty; <hi>Words of Reproof,</hi> break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them off from Sin; <hi>Words of Comfort,</hi> raiſing them up from under Sorrow. They ſpeaking unto God <hi>Words of Confeſſion,</hi> bewailing Sin; <hi>Words of Petition,</hi> depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating Vengeance, and imploring pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and healing Grace; <hi>Words of Praiſe and Thankſgiving,</hi> celebrative of his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and his Goodneſs. Not to quote the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and other Portions of Holy Scripture for Inſtances; I ask, what Chriſtian, of any Senſe, knows not this by his Experience? Experience, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39190:10"/>maketh all things more manifeſt than Speech the moſt Excellent can do; as the leaſt Beam of the Sun better ſhews its Glory, than the richeſt Painting of it can do. Briefly then; <hi>the Deaf and the Dumb, be Demoniacks.</hi> They are Strangers to God, who hear not oft from Him, and ſpeak not oft to Him. Who hear him not ſaying, <hi>Seek ye my Face!</hi> And whom he hears not anſwering, <hi>Thy Face, Lord, we will ſeek!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">(5.) <hi>Ambition to pleaſe Him,</hi> is impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Acquaintance with him. His <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is perfect Freedom,</hi> and his Friend's higheſt Ambition. <hi>Let me not love thee, if I love thee not,</hi> ſaith our Engliſh Pſalmiſt. <hi>Let me not ſerve thee, if I ſerve thee not,</hi> ſaith every true Iſraelite. Pleaſing God, is by doing his Will, and bearing it promptly and patiently. <hi>Doing his Will of Precept,</hi> after ſound Knowledg of it, and full Conſent unto it. Both, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally,</hi> as to Times, and as to the Precepts themſelves; and <hi>regularly,</hi> making it our greateſt Employment to keep the firſt and greateſt Commandments. Preferring <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Obedience,</hi> before <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> the <hi>weighty Things of the Law,</hi> before <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Cummin; Righteouſneſs and Peace,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39190:10"/>before diſputed <hi>Meat and Drink. Submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Will of Providence,</hi> is no leſs neceſſary. Submitting, without <hi>contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of its Chaſtiſements, or <hi>fainting</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them. Stupidity and Deſpondency, are both Sins and Judgments. Senſe of our Sufferings, and a proportionate Sorrow is the Grace of God both in us, and unto us. Our Duty towards him, and his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to us. Grief, and its Expreſſions, are no Offences, but when they are unquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with their due Circumſtances. When they are <hi>Diſproportionate</hi> to an inflicted ſtroke; and our Complaint is great, for a Croſs that is little, like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s anger to the Death, for no heavier loſs than that of a Gourd. When they are <hi>Indecent,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective againſt ſecond Cauſes; expreſſing Fury, and not Humility. Like thoſe of <hi>Job,</hi> and of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> who, in their Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, curſed their Birth-days, and the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of them. When they are <hi>Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate,</hi> and ſuch as argue us to be Men without Hope; as <hi>David</hi> in his ejulation for his loſt <hi>Abſalom.</hi> And, when they are <hi>Profane;</hi> taxing the Divine Juſtice, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling Providence. In ſhort; this <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience, as truly as <hi>Active,</hi> is in all true Acquaintance with God. And, as Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39190:11"/>as they ſeem, and repugnant to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature; they are more than <hi>Facilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> both of them; they are even <hi>Neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> by a good underſtanding of God's <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Dominion,</hi> his <hi>Knowledg and Wiſdom,</hi> his <hi>Goodneſs and Truth.</hi> Yea, they are <hi>Commended</hi> unto us as our Principality, and the Crown of our Glory. Accordingly, we find this to be the Language of Men Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with God; <hi>I will Walk at Liberty, for I ſeek thy Precepts! It is Good for me that I have bin Afflicted. Here I am, Let the Lord do to me as ſeemeth him good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">(6.) <hi>Dependence on Him,</hi> is alſo eſſential unto Acquaintance with God. The three known branches of Dependance, are ſo; to wit, Truſt, Faith, and Hope. <hi>Truſt</hi> in his Goodneſs, when we ſit in greateſt Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>Faith, and Aſſent</hi> unto whatſoever He ſays; and <hi>Hope, or ſweet Expectation</hi> of all He Promiſes. For, there is a real Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Him, for all the Affections which He requireth from Us. It were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming his Majeſty to demand them, if there were not that in his <hi>Nature,</hi> and that in his <hi>Works</hi> that did deſerve them. Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, their ſtate in this World requiring that they ſhould have ſomewhat to lean on; and to keep them from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39190:11"/>with outward Troubles and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Paſſions; they muſt neceſſarily <hi>Lean on the Lord, and ſtay themſelves on the God of their Salvation.</hi> As promptly therefore, as Seamen uſe their <hi>Anchor,</hi> or Souldiers their <hi>Breaſtplate</hi> and <hi>Shield</hi> and <hi>Helmet;</hi> Saints do exerciſe theſe Vertues, which the Scripture repreſenteth by thoſe Names; <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.17. Their Life is ſpent in <hi>Contemplation</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections, which make a proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Confidence; and in <hi>practical Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of them: Namely, of the <hi>unerring Wiſdom,</hi> which infallibly knows all our Wants, and underſtandeth what are the beſt Supplies. Of the <hi>unſpotted Goodneſs,</hi> which is ſurely concerned for us; and taketh care for Creatures leſs than our ſelves, for Ravens, for Sparrows, for the Graſs of the Field. Of the <hi>unqueſtionable Power,</hi> to which all things are poſſible; and nothing is difficult, tho by us much is unintelligible. Power, that can do more than we can know; and is worthy to be truſted further than we can ſee. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet ſaith all in a Word, <hi>They that know thy Name, will put their Truſt in thee!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:39190:12"/>
               <p n="7">(7.) <hi>Humility before Him,</hi> is in all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God. His Acquaintance is a Holy Familiarity, that doth not <hi>breed</hi> Contempt, nor <hi>brook</hi> it. Tho the Majeſty of Heaven condeſcends to acquaint it ſelf with Worms, it maketh them to know their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The Proud, whoſe <hi>Souls are lifted up,</hi> are oppoſed to <hi>Believers who walk with God,</hi> Hab. 2.11. And, it is certain, that exiled Devils are the proudeſt, and glorious Angels the moſt humble Creatures. Theſe latter would be Nothing, that God may be All; theſe Fiends would be All, and have God to be Nothing. Whomſoever he adopts into his Favour, God always qualifieth with a ſutable Nature. And, we know, that <hi>great Honours do melt down ingenuous Spirits.</hi> The Grace which ſetteth Crowns upon their Heads, doth make them fall on their Knees. And the more they are magnified, the farther they be from magnifying of themſelves. <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> being invited to eat the King's Bread, debaſingly ſtiles himſelf a <hi>dead Dog. Abigail,</hi> when ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with a Call to be the King's Wife, profeſſeth it too high a Preferment for her, to be his Servant; <hi>Let thy Handmaid be a Servant, to waſh the Feet of the Servants of my Lord!</hi> In a Word; <hi>David</hi> is told, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39190:12"/>
                  <hi>God would build him an Houſe, and eſtabliſh his Sons on the Throne after him;</hi> and doth it not ſwell him up? No, we find not that ever his Lips dropped more ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Words; <hi>Who am I, O Lord God, and what is my Houſe?</hi> So, unto <hi>Job,</hi> God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in excelling Glory and Majeſty; and what is the Effect? <hi>I abhor my ſelf,</hi> ſaith that excellent Saint. <hi>Lord, I am Hell,</hi> ſaid the Martyr <hi>Hooper,</hi> as he was aſcending to Heaven! Pride, is the Sin which is leaſt of all conſiſtent with God's Friendſhip. It is as much againſt his <hi>Laws</hi> as any; and more againſt his <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Sovereignty.</hi> It's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the groſſeſt Defiance of his <hi>Providence;</hi> receiving its Croſſes with no leſs than Rage, and its Bleſſings with no better than Diſdain! It's the Sin that God is not content to <hi>ruin,</hi> but delighteth alſo to <hi>ſhame.</hi> Not ſending Lions, but Lice, to eat up an <hi>Herod;</hi> not Wolves and Bears, but Goats and Flies, to aſſault a <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> not an <hi>Anakim,</hi> but a very Stripling, to fell a <hi>Goliah.</hi> I ſhall ſuggeſt no more to prove ſo plain a Truth, that, an unhum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Man is unacquainted with God, as ſurely as with himſelf. The God that caſts down his choiceſt Favorites, when they lift up themſelves. Smites an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzias,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:39190:13"/>with a Plague of Leproſy. Makes the Tumor of a <hi>David</hi> coſt ſeventy thouſand Lives. And lets looſe the Devil, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the ſwelling of an <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> The God who judgeth all, who do not judg them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and humbleth all, who do not humble themſelves, both as <hi>Creatures,</hi> and as <hi>Guilty Ones.</hi> Who, where he finds not an humble Heart of ours, faileth not to ſhow a mighty Hand of his own! One, that never fails to break the Heart, or the Bones. Whoſe Oracles do proclaim no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more loudly, than that <hi>before Honour is Humility!</hi> And do thus anſwer to ſuch as ask for his Livery; <hi>Be ye clothed with Humility!</hi> But <hi>with fear and trembling,</hi> it muſt be nextly ſaid,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God was loſt in</hi> Adam <hi>the firſt Man.</hi> We were created in God's Likeneſs; and, being qualified, were then poſſeſſed of his Friendſhip. But, that State being <hi>Natural,</hi> was <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</hi> With a <hi>Power</hi> of ſtanding in it, there was a <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of falling from it. For, invincible Perſeverance, is the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of ſupernatural Grace. Wherefore, being ſeduced, <hi>Adam</hi> ſoon rebelled; as, without any Temptation offered, <hi>Satan</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39190:13"/>the Tempter revolted. Tempted Man, tho placed ſo near unto God; tho he was a bright Repreſentative both of his <hi>Purity,</hi> and of his <hi>Felicity,</hi> was corrupted by a <hi>ſimple Suaſion;</hi> was vanquiſhed by a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Temptation,</hi> and the very firſt. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that he was furniſhed with ſufficient Strength to have repelled a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, he fell by one. He ſinned; and, by violating <hi>God's Law,</hi> deprived himſelf of <hi>God's Image;</hi> in the Place whereof ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the <hi>Pourtraiture of Satan.</hi> By his <hi>Infidelity,</hi> he became an Accuſer of God; and that, both of Unkindneſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth. By his <hi>Pride,</hi> he turns an Uſurper of Divine Prerogatives; and incurs the Arrogance that made Devils of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. By his <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> he made himſelf as diſingenuous as they; who had not greater Bands of Love to break than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. By his <hi>Contempt</hi> of the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Juſtice, he no leſs inſolently and audaciouſly defied his Creator. By his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable <hi>Folly,</hi> in parting with God's Favour and Image for ſo deſpicable a Thing as that which was his Lure, he as much reproached his Underſtanding. And, to name no more; by his <hi>Cruelty</hi> to himſelf, and to his vaſt Progeny, he became a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39190:14"/>Murderer full like to his Tempter. For, he being the Natural and Moral Principle of all Men; his Rebellion was of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Guilt and Stain to all his Generation. Nor was it hard, that, being in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him, and having a Title to the <hi>Benefits promiſed</hi> to his Obedience, we ſhould alſo be liable to the <hi>Curſe threatned</hi> upon his Diſobedience. In ſhort; thus were the Fountain and Streams, the Root and the Off-ſpring corrupted. With a Corruption ſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> that, of all (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending by ordinary Generation) it miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth no Individual; ſo <hi>Subtile,</hi> that it pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into all the Powers of the Soul; ſo <hi>Contagious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Bates's Harmony, <hi>p.</hi> 40.</note> that it infects all the Actions; and ſo <hi>Obſtinate,</hi> that only Omnipotence can heal it!</p>
               <p>And till ſuch time as it doth heal it, what Acquaintance hath Man with God? What Communion hath our Darkneſs with his Light? <hi>By Nature we are Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath,</hi> actively and paſſively; Hating, and hated of God. <hi>God's Wrath abideth on us,</hi> Joh. 3.33. and our <hi>Carnal Mind is Enmity againſt God,</hi> Rom. 8.7. So far is unrenewed Man from Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God, that the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares him to be <hi>without God in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39190:14"/>World;</hi> and a very <hi>hater of God!</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, it muſt be added, <hi>with Joy and Gladneſs of Heart,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for us again, by Chriſt the ſecond A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> The impoſſibility of our recovering it by ought of our own, needs little De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration. <hi>Fall'n Angels,</hi> could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain theirs; and <hi>Dead Men</hi> had not more Wiſdom or Strength to raiſe themſelves. Our <hi>Minds</hi> being depraved with Ignorance and Error; and our <hi>Wills</hi> with Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety to God; thoſe Principles of our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being corrupted, what could we do towards a ſecond Rectitude? Beſides, the Acquaintance of God is the Happineſs of Man. The Happineſs that he forfeited by Sin; and, whoſe Forfeiture the Law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted. Not admitting the Sinner to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God's Favour, but requiring that his Crime ſhould be puniſhed according to its Quality; that is, to <hi>Extremity</hi> and to <hi>Eternity.</hi> Inſomuch, that the Divine Goodneſs was a <hi>ſealed Spring;</hi> and all its kind Effects were reſtrained by our Guilt, till our Sin was expiated by a valuable, or rather, invaluable Sacrifice. By that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Obedience of his Son, which more
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39190:15"/>pleaſed God, than the Rebellion of Men and Devils provoked Him!</p>
               <p>Herewith, as <hi>an Offering and Sacrifice of ſweet ſmelling Savour,</hi> the incenſed <hi>Wrath of God</hi> was appeaſed, the <hi>Hand-writing of the Law</hi> which was againſt us was blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, and <hi>Peace was made.</hi> Herewith, as <hi>a Price moſt precious and honourable to God,</hi> all that by Sin we had forfeited, was redeemed; a <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> which is <hi>all our Salvation and all our Deſire,</hi> is ſealed and made ſure; <hi>a new and living Way of return into God's Acquaintance</hi> is opened. This is God's Gift, but thro Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Bleſſing and Honour, and Glory and Power, be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb, for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God is now offered to Men.</hi> To Men, both, <hi>without Strength,</hi> and unable to help themſelves, (any more than a diſordered Clock to mend it ſelf:) and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly,</hi> and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy that God ſhould help them, (any more than the loſt Angels.) <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Angels, John Baptiſt, Chriſt himſelf,</hi> and <hi>his Apoſtles,</hi> all proclaim this <hi>Good will to Men.</hi> The Heavens are not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39190:15"/>ſo thick ſet with Stars, as the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with Invitations, to return unto Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God. With <hi>Counſels,</hi> with <hi>Commands,</hi> with <hi>Directions,</hi> with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Obſecrations</hi> and Intreaties to us, to haſten into it. All of them manifeſting, that we are not, as Devils, in a State re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſs. That every one of us is called to Repentance, tho not one of them is ſo! And that, altho <hi>God giveth not unto all Men, that Grace which eventually ſaveth them,</hi> yet, <hi>he giveth them what leads to that which is ſaving;</hi> and, all who go without his <hi>ſpecial Gifts,</hi> do meritoriouſly procure the loſs of 'em, by their not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving his <hi>common Ones,</hi> which they do receive. <hi>God mocks not any Man, till he be finally rejected by him; and he finally rejects not any, till, unto his natural hardneſs of Heart, he addeth what is voluntary.</hi> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that Mens <hi>Cannot,</hi> is their <hi>Will-not;</hi> tho they are under <hi>perfect Impotence,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he true Reaſon that they acquaint not themſelves with God, is their <hi>malignant Wilfulneſs.</hi> And, every Sinner's <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion</hi> is verily his <hi>Option. O Iſrael, thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf!</hi> Be it awfully and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tinctly conſidered in the next place;</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:39190:16"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther broken by every preſumptuous Actual Sin. Original</hi> Sin firſt brake it, and <hi>Actual</hi> Sin encreaſeth the Breach. This it doth, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially;</hi> for as it deſerves, God makes it to be, its own Puniſhment. He Forſakes ſuch as Forſake him; and puniſheth Strangeneſs with Eſtrangement. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding thoſe his Communications, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Acquaintance dies. Saying of them who <hi>Perverſely</hi> will not, that <hi>Penally</hi> they ſhall not, be Acquainted with him! Likewiſe, <hi>Naturally</hi> it doth it; for, what is Sinning but a kind of <hi>going out from the Preſence of the Lord?</hi> A <hi>turning away of the Simple;</hi> a <hi>Departing from the Living God;</hi> a ſaying to God, <hi>Depart from us!</hi> As oft as we Sin, we act the part of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature; and thereby, an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> Man makes himſelf more a <hi>Child of Wrath,</hi> than he was by Nature. And, a <hi>Regenerate</hi> one brings himſelf back, in ſome Degree, to what he was by Nature; even a <hi>ſtranger unto God.</hi> Indeed there are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Sinning; the loweſt, is that of <hi>Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> the higheſt is ſinning <hi>Wilfully and with pure Delight:</hi> From this latter, every Regenerate Man is freed; but from the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39190:16"/>former, no one is. Now, in the Language of the Goſpel, he liveth <hi>without Sin,</hi> who liveth <hi>without wilful Sin,</hi> and doth not <hi>Fall into Groſs Sin.</hi> Who ſo-acts-up to his Light and Grace received, that though he hath his <hi>daily Infirmities,</hi> yet he is bright and clean from <hi>ſcandalous Sins.</hi> Which be they, that do principally create a diſtance, and ſeparate between God and his Servants. In ſhort; <hi>One Sin deſtroys much good.</hi> And the exclamation is as juſt in this caſe as in any; <hi>Behold how great a Matter a little fire kindleth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God is Entred by Repentance and Faith.</hi> Theſe, though they are not the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of God's exalting us unto his Acquaintance, they are neceſſary <hi>Qualifications</hi> in all whom He will exalt unto it. <hi>Repentance</hi> includes Heart-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sorrow for Sin, and ſincere Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to forſake it. Neceſſary this is, by virtue of the Divine <hi>Command,</hi> and by the <hi>Condecency</hi> and fitneſs which it is of, both unto God, and unto our ſelves. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto God;</hi> for, neither would it become his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> to make us a ſecond time his Friends, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our Grief and Shame for having made our ſelves his Enemies: nor could it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39190:17"/>with his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> to Forgive and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance us, while ſo Sinful and Senſeleſs. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto our ſelves</hi> alſo; for if Unrelenting and Unreformed, what ſo much as Inclination is in us to Acquaintance with God? Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digals never liſt to return to their Father, till their Hearts are broken for Running away from him. Again, <hi>Faith in our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi> is no leſs Commanded, or leſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous. A Faith ſeated in Mind and Heart; and receiving Chriſt in all parts of his Office, which are inſeparably connexed. Unto this Grace, Juſtification is ſpecially attributed; and it's certain, that none but the Juſtified are Acquainted with God. Eminently this Grace contains the Seed of Evangelical Obedience. And is that which <hi>Crucifies our Luſts, Overcomes the World, Quenches the Darts of the Devil, and Works by the Love of God.</hi> Without which, what Acquaintance with God? <hi>The God who is of purer Eyes than to behold Evil:</hi> and conſequently, <hi>Without this Faith is not to be pleaſed.</hi> To be pleaſed with us, or to be pleaſed and ſerved by us. Briefly then, the Impenitent and the Unbelieving are Swine, to whom the Pearl of God's Acquaintance neither is, or can be vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed. <hi>He that Repents not, muſt Periſh!
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39190:17"/>He that Believeth not, the Wrath of God abideth on him!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God, is preſerved by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of his Ordinances and the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Graces.</hi> Ordinances, or God's ordained Means, muſt be uſed. Without theſe, we are not <hi>Brought into</hi> his Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor <hi>Kept in</hi> it. It is an Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which in this Life is but <hi>Imperfect;</hi> and, not as in Heaven, <hi>Immediate.</hi> The holy Word, is the Seed of which it is Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got; and the <hi>Food</hi> by which it is Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Wherefore, as all the Ordinances are propounded by God, with a <hi>Promiſe</hi> and a <hi>Threat;</hi> ſo, they are followed by the Friends of God with <hi>Hope</hi> and with <hi>Fear. Experience of Benefit by them,</hi> edgeth their Appetites unto them. <hi>O God, early will I ſeek thee, my Soul thirſteth, my Fleſh longeth, to ſee thy Power and thy Glory, ſo as I have ſeen thee in the Sanctuary,</hi> Pſal. 61.1, 2. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> alſo compels them; the Hunger of their Souls, like that of Bodies, maketh them to break thro Stone Walls, to get unto Ordinances. For they feel Decays; and much lacking unto all their <hi>Graces;</hi> and much ground loſt in many of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,</hi> between Fleſh and Spirit. And they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39190:18"/>know, that there is no Help without <hi>Watching at God's Gates, waiting at the Poſts of his Doors;</hi> and it's there they muſt <hi>find Life and Favour of the Lord,</hi> Prov. 8.34, 35. Beſides, there is in them <hi>a Nature and an Inſtinct,</hi> which, without ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, carries them unto Ordinances. As it carrieth new-born Children to the Dugs; and Chickens, as ſoon as they are out of the Shell, to the ſhrowd of the Hen's Wing. A Native inbred Deſire, carries the one and the other. 1 Pet. 2.2. <hi>As New-born Babes, deſire the ſincere Milk of the Word that ye may Grow:</hi> i. e. Let in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>Appetite</hi> draw you! Babes, are not urged to the Breaſt with Syllogiſms. In ſhort; the ſame thing that maketh Fiſhes to keep in the Waters that breed them, maketh the Friends of God to keep to the Ordinances which convert them. And to prefer a <hi>Threſhold</hi> in them, before a <hi>Throne</hi> without them.</p>
               <p>It deſerves our beſt Conſideration, as plain a Truth as it is; that, in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances we ſpeak of, [in <hi>Reading, Hearing the Word, Celebrating the Lords Supper, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, Prayer, and holy Conference;</hi>] God draweth near unto Us, and We draw near unto God. <hi>God draweth near unto us;</hi> the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39190:18"/>Ordinances are called the very <hi>Face of God,</hi> Gen. 4.16. <hi>Cain went out from the preſence of the Lord;</hi> that is, he forſook the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of his Worſhip. The Ordinances, wherein his Promiſe is <hi>to COME unto us,</hi> Ex. 20.24. to <hi>MEET with us, and COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE with us,</hi> Ex. 25.22. Though God be every where Preſent, and fills Heaven and Earth with his Preſence, it is ſaid of old, that <hi>his Glory filled the Temple,</hi> the Place of his Worſhip; ſignifying his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſpecial Preſence of Love, and Grace, and Influence upon Souls, to be in his Ordinances. Theſe therefore are the great King's Preſence-Chambers! Again, <hi>We draw near unto God in Ordinances,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Our Worſhipping in them, is named our <hi>Coming and Appearing before God,</hi> Pſal. 42.2. Worſhippers, are ſtiled <hi>a People NEAR unto Him;</hi> and Men Idolatrous or Profane, are ſaid to be <hi>FAR from Him.</hi> It's true, the Worſt of Men are at no Local di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from God; nor is it a Local nearneſs that we affirm God's Servants to enjoy in Ordinances, but a Spiritual one. <hi>He is not Far from any one of us; in Him we Live, Move, and have our Being.</hi> He is <hi>Over all</hi> by his Power, <hi>Through all</hi> the World by his Providence, <hi>In all</hi> his Saints by his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39190:19"/>Spirit. The Spirit, by whom they are Brought and Kept nigh Him, and are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited with frequence to Draw moſt near to Him in his Ordinances. Which, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>'s <hi>Ladder,</hi> have their Top in Heaven, though their Foot on Earth. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as God deſcends to us, we do Aſcend to God. <hi>The Lord is nigh to all that Call upon Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit, without <hi>the Exerciſe of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> vain is the Uſe of Ordinances. Such Uſe, is very Profaneſs; and no <hi>Mean,</hi> but the <hi>Bane</hi> of Acquaintance with God. For, what is ſuch Worſhip, but <hi>Lies and Deceit?</hi> Hoſ. 11. <hi>ult.</hi> Think we, that we can Come to God, a Spirit, upon Bodily Feet? Or, that there is any beneficial Approach to Him, but with the Heart? Or, with any thing of the Heart, but the Holy Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of it? Briefly, thus; in every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we muſt ſet forward <hi>Repentance;</hi> It is unto his Mourners, that in Ordinances God cometh down with Comforts; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. We muſt act <hi>Faith;</hi> what we Feel our ſelves to Want, we muſt Believe God able and willing to Give. To wit, for the ſake of Chriſt, who hath paid for it on Earth, and pleads for it in Heaven. The Scripture bids him <hi>not think to Receive any
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39190:19"/>thing,</hi> who in Ordinances <hi>asketh without Faith and Wavering;</hi> Jam. 1.6, 7. We muſt act <hi>Hope;</hi> this is the Waiting Grace. It is an Expectation, that is <hi>Certain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe built on the Rock of Divine Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and <hi>Quickning</hi> both Deſire and Action, becauſe of its Objects attractive excellency; and <hi>Quieting</hi> alſo, till God's time of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing it doth come; becauſe Hope is it ſelf a very Foretaſte of its Object's ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! And there is a <hi>Rejoicing in Hope,</hi> as well as in Poſſeſſion. No wonder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that there is a <hi>Patience of Hope,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Exerciſe whereof in an Ordinance, our Hearts be either Frozen and Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, or Furious and Impatient. <hi>When we Hope for God's Salvation, then we do his Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 119.166. We muſt alſo put forth <hi>Love;</hi> for, this is the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Grace. By its Deſire we run to an Object, by its Delight we reſt in it. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, the firſt act of Love, is as Thirſt; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, which is its other Act, is Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. An Ordinance without theſe is as a Feaſt where there's no Appetite, or Eating. But, what ſaith our Saviour? <hi>If a Man Love me he ſhall be Beloved of my Father, and I will Love him, and will Manifeſt my ſelf unto him. We will Come unto him and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39190:20"/>make our Abode with him,</hi> Joh. 14.21, 23. We muſt likewiſe expreſs <hi>Humility;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our <hi>Natural diſtance</hi> from God, which is never to be reduced, and our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſtance,</hi> which is but in part removed. Who can meaſure the Diſtance between <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi> and <hi>Finite?</hi> Between a God, and a Creature? Or, the Diſtance that is between <hi>Perfect Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>little beſide Guilt and Filth?</hi> Between Him in whoſe ſight Angels are not clean, and Creatures that proclaim themſelves to be Sinks of Sin; and to need no leſs than a Fountain of Grace! The Man <hi>unto whom God will look</hi> in any Ordinance, <hi>is the Poor and Contrite in Spirit that trembleth at his Word,</hi> Iſa. 66.2. Then only we Worſhip, when our <hi>Souls bow down,</hi> and our <hi>Spirits Kneel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God our Maker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, is Acquaintance with God main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. By his Communications unto us, and our Exerciſing Graces and Performing Duties toward Him. A bleſſed Recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wherein <hi>He deſcending</hi> to us in a way of <hi>Bounty,</hi> we <hi>aſcend</hi> up unto him in a way of <hi>Duty! Happy is the People that is in ſuch a Caſe! Happy is the People whoſe God is the Lord!</hi> Wherefore, laſtly,</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:39190:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>Acquaintance with God is Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and broken by theſe particulars.</hi> Theſe, into which we eaſily Fall; and under which we muſt deeply Suffer as oft as we do ſo. Namely,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Preſumptuous Sins.</hi> Sins commited, not by the Error of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and named <hi>Sins of Ignorance</hi> or <hi>Incogitancy;</hi> nor by the raſhneſs and precipitance of the <hi>Affections,</hi> and named <hi>Sins of Infirmity;</hi> but, committed by the <hi>rebellious Will;</hi> which notwithſtanding the Dictate of the Mind offered to it, is ſwayed by the Luſt of bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Affection, and ruſhes into the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing that God hates! Theſe, bear the name of <hi>Preſumptuous Sins.</hi> And, ſuch is their Malignity, that they alienate God from the Soul, and the Soul from God. They are ſaid to <hi>Separate,</hi> Iſa. 59.2. And, know we not their Effect, upon the Man of God's own Heart? His own words do argue, that, they made him fear himſelf to be a Caſt-a-way. <hi>Caſt me not away from thy Preſence, and take not thy Holy Spirit from me,</hi> Pſal. 51.11. In ſhort; where wilful Sins do not die, no Acquaintance with God can Live. It muſt lay us in a Swoon, till their Mortification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Rejected Duties.</hi> Known Duties, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39190:21"/>as to <hi>Frequence,</hi> or as to <hi>Fervence</hi> in them. As ſlow as the Lord is unto Wrath, he will bear no ſuch Slights of his Love. For, what a Contempt is <hi>weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Supream King's Service, and Benefactor's Acquaintance?</hi> What a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy is it, in practice to ſay, <hi>We are Lords, and will come no more unto thee!</hi> Jer. 2.31. What a ſenſleſs Iniquity is it, as well as a Contumelious? For never could any anſwer to God's Query, <hi>VVhat have I done unto thee, and wherein have I wearied thee?</hi> Mic. 6.3. If we have full Stomachs, and loath God's Honeycombs, we ſhall not go long without feeling his Rods and Scorpions. The Vials of his Anger ſhall be poured out, and the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Aids and Comforts of his grieved Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit be ſuſpended. It's more than proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that till we ſtir up our ſelves, and fill our Life with Duties, and our Duties with Graces, we ſhall find our ſelves emptied of our Hopes of Heaven, and filled with the Fears of Hell. <hi>My ſeldom-praying hath made me ſo often-deſpairing,</hi> ſaith one; <hi>My long Faſts from Duty, have taken away all my Appetite unto it.</hi> And, what ſaith another? <hi>For my ſake, let all Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Coldneſs in Ordinances; it hath been
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39190:21"/>the Death of my Hopes, and giveth me a Life of nothing but Fears.</hi> It is ſaid of ſome <hi>Sovereign Potions,</hi> that if taken cold, their Virtue is Malignant; they rather <hi>kill</hi> than <hi>heal.</hi> I am much more certain, that the Ordinances, which, being attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Zeal, <hi>lift up toward Heaven;</hi> when Lukewarmneſs obtains, they do <hi>throw us clean contrary.</hi> As many as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a flouriſhing Acquaintance with him, let them <hi>ſeek the Lord continually, and with all their Heart and their Soul.</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that all <hi>drawing back tends to its Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition!</hi> Laſtly,</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Purſued Vanities.</hi> By Vanities, I intend this World's Idols. <hi>Senſual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> which are but Swines Delights. <hi>Riches,</hi> of Gold, that is but Duſt; and of Pearl, which is no more than the Sea's Froth. <hi>Honour and Praiſe of Men,</hi> which is but their unſeen Conceit, and their favourable Breath. Of theſe, the condemned Purſuit is ſuch as is <hi>Abſolute and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimate,</hi> neither <hi>Submiſſive</hi> nor <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate.</hi> When we proſecute them, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved any manner of way to gain them. Making them our higheſt Ambition. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of their being withheld from us, by the undoubted Proprietor. And fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39190:22"/>in the deſire of them; ſo panting after them, as the Hart after the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooks. The Apoſtle's Aſſertion is thus to be taken; <hi>If any Man</hi> (thus) <hi>love the World, the Love of the Father is not in him,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.15. The Throne, and the Bed admit but one. To ſubject us to the World, is to depoſe God. To take the World into our Hearts, is to put him far from them. How much leſs, ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtle? The <hi>Friendſhip of the World, is Enmity with God; whoſoever will be a Friend of the World, is an Enemy of God!</hi> Jam. 4.4. When the Earth is interpoſed between the Sun and us, it muſt needs be Night; and when earthly things get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and our Hearts, there as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follows an Eſtrangement and Darkneſs. The Pſalmiſt's Word ſpeaks it in ſhort; <hi>The Covetous the Lord abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> Pſal. 10.3. Be it added, laſtly;</p>
               <p>They err, <hi>not knowing the Scriptures and the Grace of God;</hi> who, imagine <hi>Sins of unavoidable Infirmity,</hi> inconſiſtent with his Acquaintance and Amity. The Penitent, who reſiſts them, is not alienated by them. And, as the innumerable Moats in the Air, hinder not the deſcent of the Sun's bright and benign Beams upon us; neither do the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39190:22"/>numberleſs Failings of good Men, deprive them of the rich Conſolations of God. <hi>Sins of meer VVeakneſs, do rather excite Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than kindle VVrath;</hi> ſo far they be from interrupting Acquaintance!</p>
               <p>Which is not broken, neither, by the <hi>moderate Employments,</hi> or <hi>Comforts of this Life.</hi> The Shop, and the Plow, are not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but <hi>neceſſary.</hi> Let there be juſt Care, that the lean Kine eat not up the Fat; that, the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven be ſought, and firſt ſought;</hi> then, do <hi>civil</hi> Callings ſubſerve and not prejudice our higher <hi>Sacred</hi> One. So, for the <hi>Comforts</hi> foreſaid, they are more than <hi>Innocent,</hi> when Temperate. If we take them by the Rules of God's Word, we ſhall find them both <hi>harmleſs,</hi> and <hi>uſeful</hi> to his Frindſhip. We do ſo take them, when we <hi>chuſe</hi> none but what are of good Report; (for, <hi>he that breaks the Hedg</hi> thereof, <hi>a Serpent ſhall bite him;</hi>) and when we <hi>uſe</hi> not any, to the wounding of <hi>Piety, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity;</hi> (for, by marrying of a Wife, as well as by dallying with a Harlot, a Man breaks the Peace of God; if his Uſe of Liberty degenerates into Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and if he ſuffers it to make him break the Precepts of God.) Pleaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39190:23"/>choſen and uſed, is <hi>Health to the Navel, and Marrow to the Bones;</hi> a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to <hi>Life and Godlineſs. The Heart of the Wiſe, is,</hi> therefore, <hi>in the Houſe of ſuch Mirth.</hi> And, may I not ſay it? Look as God <hi>firſt created</hi> Man, in a Garden of Delight; He moſtly <hi>new creates</hi> him alſo, where the Voice of Joy and Gladneſs, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual as well as Spiritual, is heard. The innocent Mirth of a Chriſtian, caſteth a Luſtre on his Religion, and maketh it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive. Removeth from it the Reproach of Sowrneſs and Aſperity. Forth-ſhews its Sweetneſs and Alacrity; whereof, Men that try it not, think it to be deſtitute. Yea, and as <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Juſtin</hi> of old, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they think it to be deſtitute, they are unperſuadable to try it. Inſomuch, that Stoical and Monkiſh Auſterity, gives Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Reproach, and makes the Way of God to be blaſphemed. So far it is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning the Goſpel, from making it appear Amiable, and from winning Men to the Love of it. It was then when <hi>they that believed did eat their Meat with Gladneſs,</hi> that <hi>the Lord added daily to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved!</hi> Moroſity was never o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a back Friend to Chriſtianity!</p>
               <p>The Scruples of ſome others, do require
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39190:23"/>that this be added; <hi>ſc.</hi> that, <hi>Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God is not inconſistent with Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Doubts of his Love.</hi> The Life of it, conſiſts not in Raptures and Extacies of Joy; which God gives, as, in abſolute Soveraignty and infinite Wiſdom, he ſees fit and pleaſes. How often do <hi>Children of Light ſit in Darkneſs and ſee no Light?</hi> Clouds of Witneſſes, are every where to be found; yea, the whole Sky of the Church, is full of them. Wherefore, in a word; the <hi>natural Sun</hi> maketh Gold and Silver, where it doth not ſhine with any Luſtre. And the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> riſeth on many with Healing in his Wings, to whom he doth not, of a long time, give rapturous Senſations of the ſame. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know they well <hi>what Spirit they are of,</hi> who think the holy One to be no <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> where He is not (at the ſame time) a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2. Of <hi>the Peace and Good, following Acquaintance with God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Hebrew Dialect takes <hi>Peace,</hi> for the whole Element of Goodneſs. For no leſs than all that is deſirable. Nor can the Gain of God's Acquaintance be ſuppoſed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39190:24"/>to be leſs. <hi>Omnia habet qi habet habentem omnia.</hi> To enjoy Him who is all Good, is to enjoy no leſs than all of it. Uncreated Goodneſs giving us its Acquaintance, <hi>how ſhall it not with the ſame freely give us all things?</hi> All that is neceſſary of created Goodneſs. God is Faithful, and his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance is thus Gainful. His Friends are <hi>Kings,</hi> as well as <hi>Prieſts;</hi> and richer than the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings, who went a begging to Projectors to invent them more Pleaſures. Theſe are bleſt, with more than they can ask or think. But (becauſe Particulars are moſt affective) that we may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, in the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> hereof, to purſue it with becoming <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Vigour,</hi> attend we but theſe two Poſitions. Yet ſufficient, one would think, to reform the moſt <hi>Obſtinate in evil VVays,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the leaſt <hi>Reſolute in good Ones.</hi> The Lord clothe them with <hi>a Power which none may be able to reſist!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>The Properties which commend this Peace are many. e. gr.</hi> 1. It is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal;</hi> One, which contains all; <hi>ſc.</hi> Peace with God, with Conſcience, with Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and with Death.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:39190:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peace with God;</hi> with God, whoſe Wrath is Hell, and whoſe Peace is Heaven. A Peace, which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>paſſes all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> Phil. 4.7. This follows Acquaintance with God. When <hi>Adam</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Enmity was made; Enmity, that is a Reciprocation of Hatred. Chriſt Jeſus maketh Friendſhip, which is a Reciproca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Love! And, how? Partly, <hi>by his Blood,</hi> ſatisfying God's Juſtice, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting his Mercy for us. Partly <hi>by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> mortifying our Malice, and reviving all Grace in us. Propitiating God to us, and qualifying us for God's Love and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance! Without the firſt, God would be a <hi>conſuming Fire</hi> to us; and without the other, we ſhould never <hi>conquer our Fear,</hi> or <hi>quench our Malice</hi> againſt him. But, by means of both, there's <hi>mutual Peace.</hi> The Peace whence do ſpring the ſweet Ones fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peace with Conſcience;</hi> one leſs known by the moſt accurate <hi>Deſcription,</hi> than by the leaſt <hi>Fruition.</hi> It can be but darkly ſhadowed forth, by the livelieſt Colours of Language; but faintly repreſented by Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors. What <hi>Calmneſs</hi> is to the <hi>Sea,</hi> what <hi>Serenity</hi> is to a Day, what <hi>Health</hi> is to a Body, that Peace of Conſcience is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39190:25"/>a Man! That, and much more. But, to ſuch as have felt <hi>the Terrors of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> this Peace will little need Letters of Recommendation. For, as thoſe do make a <hi>real Tophet,</hi> and give us Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to drink; this Peace maketh a <hi>very Paradiſe,</hi> and gives us of the Wine which is drank in the Kingdom of God. <hi>Wine,</hi> that <hi>maketh merry indeed,</hi> and <hi>in nothing terrified.</hi> Becauſe, as no Winds, ſave thoſe in its own Bowels, can ever move the Earth; no Troubles, but thoſe within a Man's own Heart, can ever break it. Now, it's the Royalty of God <hi>as King,</hi> to make War and Peace; and of God as <hi>Judg,</hi> to ſpeak either Trouble or Comfort. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Conſcience as a <hi>Subject,</hi> and as an <hi>Officer,</hi> muſt <hi>hear</hi> what God ſaith; and <hi>ſpeak</hi> Peace, when he doth. And, <hi>Bleſſed are they who hear its joyful ſound!</hi> Unto them is given alſo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peace with Creatures.</hi> When Man <hi>rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſly</hi> took up Arms againſt God, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>loyally</hi> turn'd to fight againſt Man. It became them as <hi>Subjects,</hi> to eſpouſe the Quarrel of their Soveraign. And, as his <hi>Hoſt</hi> or <hi>Army</hi> to fight his Battels; all of them in their Courſes. This they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, from the firſt; and this they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39190:25"/>ſtill do. From the higheſt Cherubin to the pooreſt Worm, and very inanimate Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Creation, all ſtand in Battel-ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray againſt us, till we lay down our Arms againſt their Lord and ours. But upon our Reconciliation to God, their War is ended; Angels Love us, all the reſt do ſome way ſerve us, none do Hurt us. <hi>The Stones of the Field, and the Beaſts,</hi> are <hi>Friends</hi> again with us; and that confirmed by a <hi>League,</hi> Job 5.23. <hi>The Sucking Child may play on the Hole of the Aſp; and the Weaned Child put his Hand on the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice Den;</hi> Iſa. 11.8. True; the <hi>Tameſt</hi> of them may <hi>Wound us,</hi> by accident; and the <hi>Wildeſt be our Death,</hi> by their natural Fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but, neither of them ſhall ever break their League, and Hurt us. The King who commiſſioneth them, engageth, that they ſhall do <hi>nothing but what ſhall turn to our Good,</hi> Rom. 8.28. Inſomuch, that a Man Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with God, <hi>dwells ſafe from fear of Evil,</hi> while he lives in the Place of Dragons, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. ult. Nor is this all; there remains,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peace with Death;</hi> which, conſidered in a natural Reſpect, is a <hi>Rending aſunder Soul and Body;</hi> the things whoſe Union, is the neareſt and deareſt in all the Creation.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39190:26"/>And conſidered in a Penal reſpect, is <hi>Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels;</hi> for, what leſs is <hi>Sin's Wages,</hi> which is Death's common Name? In both reſpects, it will be acknowledged to be a <hi>King of Terrors.</hi> A <hi>Dread Soveraign,</hi> to all over whom it doth Reign. But, the <hi>King-on-Zion-Hill</hi> is He who alone doth great Wonders; and, for his Favourites, <hi>Bindeth this King of Terrors in Chains, this cruel Prince in Fetters of Iron.</hi> Saying, <hi>Touch not mine anonited, and do my People no harm!</hi> Yea, not content to foil this Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luon, and deſtroyer, as an <hi>Enemy;</hi> He changeth its Nature, and makes it a very <hi>Friend</hi> unto his Friends. <hi>Death is Yours,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle to ſuch; that is, your <hi>Friend and Servant.</hi> Thus <hi>Catholick,</hi> is the bleſſed Peace that we ſpeak of; with <hi>God above,</hi> with <hi>Conſcience within,</hi> with <hi>all the Creatures in this World,</hi> and with Death our <hi>Exodus,</hi> or going out of the World. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Property of it is this;</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a <hi>Fruitful</hi> Peace. All manner of Fruit it bears. Fruit of <hi>Praiſe</hi> unto God, and of <hi>Profit</hi> unto Men, and of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> unto God, Men, and Angels. Hence, is that <hi>Joy in Heaven</hi> made, over one Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39190:26"/>who, acquainting his Soul with God, Enters into this Peace, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. Yea, hence it was, that, Jeſus Chriſt grudged not the <hi>Blood of his Croſs,</hi> to purchaſe this Peace. Blood which he would not have ſhed, but for one of ſuch Benefit as <hi>paſſeth all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks of this Peace, and, ſo by the foregoing Property this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be. Wherefore, I proceed;</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a <hi>Durable</hi> Peace. If any thing, Immortality muſt enhanſe Value; Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingneſs muſt make things of Value to be Invaluable. And as for this Peace, it is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, if Divine Truth be Inviolable. Hear it ſpeaking in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>The Mountains ſhall depart and the Hills be removed, but my Kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the Covenant of my Peace be removed, ſaith the Lord that hath Mercy on thee.</hi> And in Jer. 32.40. <hi>I will make an Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with them, that I will not turn away from them to do them good; and I will put my Fear in their Hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me. Aſtoniſhing</hi> Grace! <hi>I will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, and They ſhall-not!</hi> This Peace is as much ſtronger than <hi>Adam</hi>'s, as <hi>God with us in our Nature</hi> is ſtronger than that <hi>earthly Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:39190:27"/>
               <p n="4">4. It's an <hi>Incomparable</hi> Peace. Rarity, addeth Sweetneſs to Honey; and the good things which are not to be Matched, are hard to be Rated. But, is this Peace to be parallel'd? What, <hi>did God ſpare one of the Angels that ſinned?</hi> Did He excuſe one from the <hi>Chains of Darkneſs,</hi> and reſtore him to Peace? Was ever our God, <hi>the God of a Second Peace,</hi> before? The Angels Peace did not Coſt the Price wherewith ours was Bought. It was not <hi>by the Blood of Jeſus,</hi> that they were <hi>made nigh to God.</hi> It was their Happineſs not to want a Peace-maker, it is our Happineſs to have one, and one no leſs than <hi>Immanuel.</hi> Wherefore, conſequently,</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is an <hi>Admirable</hi> Peace. Our Saviour himſelf, doth expreſs his great Wonder; Joh. 3.16. <hi>God So Loved the World.</hi> The <hi>holy Angels</hi> pry into it,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> with very Aſtoniſhment, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. Aſtoniſhed at the Peace, which God's <hi>bleſſed Son</hi> died to make for <hi>rebellions Servants.</hi> The <hi>Supream Judg</hi> died to make for Malefactors. Never was Love like this Love; <hi>it paſſeth all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> And never was <hi>Peace</hi> like to this Peace, <hi>the Knowledg whereof is high, we cannot attain it. In the Day of Judgment,</hi> wherein it ſhall
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39190:27"/>be fully Manifeſted, <hi>God will be admired in his Saints.</hi> i. e. Admired by <hi>Joying-Angels,</hi> by <hi>Envying-Devils and Reprobates,</hi> and by <hi>Praiſing-Saints</hi> themſelves, for the Glory of the Peace to which He advanceth them. Nevertheleſs, miſtake not this, as though, before that Day, we were to have little Peace; but know that, in Truth,</p>
               <p n="6">6. It is a <hi>Preſent</hi> Peace alſo. You are no ſooner Acquainted with God, but it is Yours. You have the <hi>ſure Grant</hi> of it, tho you have not ſo ſoon the <hi>ſweet Senſe</hi> of it. <hi>There is no Condemnation to them that are in Chriſt,</hi> though their Fear be that there is nothing elſe to them! Nor is it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of notice; that, this is never que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned by them in their Extremities; but, that, if they do <hi>Believe in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they are <hi>Juſtified by the Faith of Chriſt.</hi> And, if their ſuſpected <hi>Faith be ſound,</hi> their <hi>Joy</hi> ought to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable and Full of Glory.</hi> Moreover, as paradoxal as it may ſeem, I add concerning it, as it is in this Life;</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is a <hi>Joyful</hi> Peace, and a <hi>Glorious.</hi> So the Poſſeſſors (than whom the Earth hath not more credible Witneſſes) do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim. <hi>We have Peace with God; And</hi> what
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39190:28"/>then? <hi>We Rejoice, and not only ſo, but we Glory,</hi> Rom. 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>We Rejoice with Joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. They know that they Ought, and they Chide themſelves for the Delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when they do not; <hi>Why art thou Caſt down O my Soul? why art thou Diſquieted?</hi> Pſal. 42. <hi>ult.</hi> q. d. Why doth not the <hi>Wine</hi> of God's Peace, <hi>Chear thy Heart?</hi> Why doth not its <hi>Oil, make thy Face to ſhine?</hi> Are <hi>Guilts</hi> thy Trouble? God pardons the Penitent. Are <hi>Luſts</hi> thy Plagues? God ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues them in thoſe that ſeek to Him. <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> remain; but God is Healing them. <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> remain; but God is Conquering them. <hi>Temptations</hi> remain; but God is Rebuking them. <hi>Sufferings</hi> remain; but, God is Sweetning them. Not ſuffering them to be uſeleſs; or to be unto other than very good Purpoſe; as, of <hi>Inſtructing</hi> my Mind, <hi>Humbling</hi> my Heart; <hi>Checking</hi> my Sin; <hi>Exciting</hi> my Grace; <hi>Making me more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for Glory. Let them be miſerable that can be Miſerable,</hi> ſaith Luther; <hi>my Peace is made with God, and I cannot be Miſerable.</hi> In ſhort; Joy, is <hi>a Tree of Life;</hi> and God's Peace, is Joy; his Peace on Earth is ſo. If any Temporal Good be <hi>Denied</hi> us, this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39190:28"/>takes off the Deſire of it. If any be <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed,</hi> this makes to wait the Time of it. And whatever is <hi>Granted,</hi> this Sweetens the Uſe of it. No ſuch <hi>Anodyne</hi> is to be found, no ſuch <hi>Medicine</hi> as the Peace of God. This Peace He giveth to ſuch as Acquaint themſelves with Him, <hi>in the Houſe of their Pilgrimage.</hi> As to what more He giveth of his Royal Bounty, when He takes them up into <hi>his own Houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> this only ſhall be ſaid for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; It vaſtly tranſcends our Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and, <hi>the one half cannot be told.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>The Gift of this Peace to all that are Acquainted with God, is unqueſtionable.</hi> Even ſelf-evident; and needing no Proof. <hi>Heathens</hi> knew, and taught the moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Welfare of Men acquainted with God. <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> do blazon it. <hi>Account God the ſupream Rewarder, and Reverence him accordingly; then ſhalt thou have all Good, and fear no Evil,</hi> ſays the firſt. <hi>He is ſure to be a Free-man, that kindly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits himſelf to God his Soveraign,</hi> ſaith the other. <hi>Deo parere eſt Libertas.</hi> Senec. de Yit. Beat. Yea, <hi>the Devil,</hi> of old, did acknowledg it; <hi>Job</hi> 1.9. <hi>Doth</hi> Job <hi>Fear
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39190:29"/>God for nought? Haſt thou not made an Hedg about him?</hi> The Father of Lies ſpake this truth, though for his own Ends; <hi>q. d.</hi> All the Powers of Hell cannot break his Peace, that is a Friend of <hi>the God of Peace. As many as do know God, they proclaim Him to be thus Good;</hi> and no ſmall part of the Scriptures conſiſteth of their Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! Beſides, how doth the <hi>Nature of God</hi> certify it? <hi>God is Love,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs is his Delight.</hi> And is it poſſible, that infinite Bounty ſhould leſs richly feaſt it ſelf with its Redeemed? How ſure doth the <hi>Divine Word</hi> make it? How faſt doth <hi>the Oath</hi> of God bind it? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. How ſolemnly does He in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> confirm it? Unbelief would be almoſt as <hi>impoſſible,</hi> as it is <hi>unrighteous,</hi> if all this were duly weighed by us! I therefore haſten to my principal Buſineſs; which is,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <head>Exhortation.</head>
               <p>But, after all that hath been ſaid, needs any Man to be preſſed, to <hi>acquaint himſelf with God?</hi> What, is there any Man that believes not this Report? Or, believing it,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39190:29"/>will dare to deny or delay ſeeking his Peace with God? <hi>Jacob</hi> hears that <hi>Eſau</hi> is coming againſt him, and he ſtraitway ſendeth Preſents, and maketh humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>Adonijah</hi> fears the Effects of King <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Wrath, and flies to the Horns of the Altar. The <hi>King of Aſſyria</hi> no ſooner falls under King <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Power, but Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers are ſent with Ropes about their Necks, to beg his <hi>Peace.</hi> In our Saviour's Parable, a <hi>King that has ten thouſand Men,</hi> heareth of one <hi>who hath twenty thouſand, coming forth againſt him;</hi> and was ſo wiſe, that while he was yet far off, he ſent and treated for Peace. The Men of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> diſpleaſe <hi>Herod;</hi> and they delay not to find an Advocate, and make a Suit for Reconciliation. What! ſhall the Peace of breathing Duſt be ſo haſtily ſought, and may any Man be ſuppoſed to be yet <hi>averſe,</hi> or ſo much as unreſolved to ſeek God's Peace? Yes, ſurely; and (of Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto God and your ſelves) I muſt ſay thus much: The Viſible Church, as well as the World, <hi>exercet Hiſtrioniam,</hi> does diſguiſe and act Parts. Two ſorts of Men comprehend all the Living; ſuch as are <hi>wholly averſe</hi> from God's Acquaintance, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39190:30"/>ſuch as are <hi>culpably defective</hi> in their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Actions for it. I except not ſuch as ſit under Ordinances of greateſt Light and Power; wherein they have moſt of Sunſhine and of Thunder. He who <hi>looks down from Heaven on us, to ſee if we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and do ſeek God:</hi> He ſeeth that <hi>all are gone aſide, and gone off from him,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>totally,</hi> or <hi>in ſuch part</hi> as I have ſaid. And, with both he hath a juſt Quarrel, and a Fearful. With both therefore, is the Buſineſs of every <hi>Ambaſſador;</hi> and to each of them I direct my Exhortation.</p>
               <p>The Lord convince both, of the <hi>Matter of Fact,</hi> that it is thus with them; and of the <hi>penal Evil</hi> of it; that it is their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Sin, and deepeſt Miſery to have it ſo. The Lord ſo prepare, and incline the Hearts of both, to take his Counſels; which are not more <hi>truly,</hi> or more <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,</hi> to our <hi>Duty</hi> than to our <hi>Intereſt,</hi> Temporal and Eternal. In ſhort; <hi>The Lord's Voice thus crieth unto both, and the Man of Wiſdom ſhall hear and do; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hear and live!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Awake; get out of the Bed of your Sloth; pull aſide the Curtains you have
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39190:30"/>drawn about you, to keep out the inviting Light.</hi> The fooliſh Virgins <hi>ſleep,</hi> and the Wiſe do <hi>ſlumber.</hi> Both, in different De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, do bind up their ſpiritual Senſes. So that, by the <hi>former,</hi> nothing of God is Heard, Seen, or Felt, from Morning to Night; and, by the <hi>latter,</hi> very little! <hi>Dream,</hi> they do both of them; but <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Argue,</hi> in this Temper they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. And, as from ſleeping <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the holy Spirit departs from them! But, Sirs, <hi>Sleep not you, as do others!</hi> Be not of them, of whom God doth complain, that they do not <hi>ſtir up themſelves;</hi> but, even as a Mad-man in a Storm, do <hi>ſleep on the top of a Maſt!</hi> Live not thoughtleſs and careleſs of God, as <hi>one with whom you have not to do!</hi> nor <hi>deſire to have to do.</hi> Say not to Him in practice, <hi>Depart from us!</hi> Be gone out of our Minds and Hearts! But, as the <hi>Spouſe, Now will I ariſe!</hi> As the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> when come to himſelf, <hi>I will ariſe.</hi> As the poor periſhing <hi>Lepers, Why ſit we here till we die?</hi> The <hi>Eaſe</hi> of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sleep, is ſhort; the <hi>Midnight-Cry</hi> ſoon breaks it. The <hi>Venom</hi> of it is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; nothing more deadly than Sleep in a Lethargy. In a word; Nothing <hi>ſlayeth</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:39190:31"/>Sinners, or <hi>woundeth</hi> Saints, more than Sloth. In ſacred Things, he who is not <hi>doing,</hi> is <hi>undoing;</hi> whoever is not buſy, is not holy. And of them who are ſo, every ſlothful Servant is more a <hi>Thief</hi> than a <hi>Servant.</hi> The ſlothful in Buſineſs, is Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſlothful out of it. God's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance is both entred and exerciſed by Diligence. Memorable is the Royal Pſalmiſt's word, <hi>Thou haſt commanded us to keep thy Precepts diligently.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Think; ſtrain your Minds in the Thoughts; Commune with your Hearts frequently and ſeriouſly, concerning the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and Neceſſity of God's Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Being come to Thinking, beware of miſpending your Thoughts; by whoſe waſte, not a few Souls are loſt. The Number being great, who mind little of Religion more than the <hi>Husks.</hi> The <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities,</hi> which ſwallow up many Mens Care, are, in Reality, no more. And in fiery Contentions about them, the moſt do ſeem rather <hi>to diſgorge their Malice,</hi> than to <hi>diſcharge their Conſcience.</hi> For, what Conſcience can dream, either, that any Way of Religion can pleaſe God,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39190:31"/>without Acquaintance with Him? Or, that Difference in thoſe Notions and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, which conſiſt with his Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, is not very tolerable without Strife and Variance? Wherefore, ſhake this Viper off from your Hands; away with the <hi>Serpent</hi> and take <hi>Fiſh,</hi> away with the <hi>Stone</hi> and take <hi>Bread.</hi> Look to <hi>the End of the Commandment, which is Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity out of a pure Heart, and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Faith unfeigned.</hi> Mind you the <hi>Soul and Body</hi> of Religion; be leſs intent upon the <hi>Garb and Dreſs.</hi> Be a thouſand times more careful to excel in Acquaintance with God, which all do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to be Saving-Religion; than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this or that Opinion, about which Men of unqueſtionable Integrity cannot agree, <hi>whether it be from Heaven, or of Men!</hi> Of theſe Things put your ſelves in remembrance; <hi>You were created to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with your Creator!</hi> Your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, his Envoy in your Hearts, tells you this. Your Minds were given you to know Him; and your Wills and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, to Chuſe and Love Him. <hi>The Son of God was ſent to die for you, and his Spirit is ſent down from Heaven to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39190:32"/>live in you, that ye might be acquainted with God!</hi> And, if you refuſe to be ſo, you vex God the Holy Ghoſt, and put God the Son to open ſhame. <hi>The Helps vouchſafed in the Goſpel for God's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, are incomparably greater than thoſe afforded under the Law.</hi> So that if you improve not your Advantages, you receive greater Damnation than Old-Teſtament Sinners. Your Sin is aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, and your Sentence will be ſo. <hi>God's Acquaintance, is great Gain; and all the World without it, is Vanity and Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> If you enjoy not God, the moſt <hi>deſpicable Inſect</hi> enjoys as much as you; and if you do enjoy Him, the <hi>higheſt Cherub</hi> enjoys no more than you. <hi>In God's Acquaintance there is great Reward, even upon Earth, where there is leaſt of it.</hi> If acquainted with Him, you can have no <hi>Wants,</hi> but he will ſupply them; no <hi>Loſſes,</hi> but he will repair them; no <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats,</hi> but he will be Second, yea Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal in them; and make the Victory as ſure as the Fight. In ſhort; <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God's Acquaintance, no Sin will die in you, and no Divine Grace will live.</hi> Without this Acquaintance, Enmity to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39190:32"/>God will be <hi>bewrayed;</hi> or, if buried, <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried alive.</hi> Heavenly Vertue, and Love of God, will not be ſeen in you; or, if it be, it will be ſeen to be but <hi>pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> not <hi>engraved.</hi> He muſt be a Man of ſuch Thought, that is ever acquainted with God. With ſuch Thought, his <hi>Heart muſt ſtir him up, and his Spirit muſt make him willing!</hi> Exod. 35.21.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Reſolve; purpoſe; let a Vote paſs in your Souls; and deliberately De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, to get and encreaſe Acquaintance with God.</hi> Reſolution is the only generous Iſſue of Thought. Which, hath never been rightly fixed <hi>upon our Objects,</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Hearts,</hi> when it is barren, and bears it not. <hi>Determine</hi> now, therefore; and <hi>fully engage</hi> to purſue Acquaintance with God. Always to conſult, is as bad as never to conſult at all. For, what is <hi>Conſultation</hi> without <hi>Action?</hi> And what can be either <hi>acted</hi> before it's <hi>attempted,</hi> or be <hi>attempted</hi> before it be <hi>reſolved?</hi> In vain I ſpeak, and in vain you hear any further, if this Reſolution be not firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled! If your Wills remain ſtill in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence, and you <hi>halt between two;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39190:33"/>God's Friendſhip, and the World's; it were more expedient that I ſhould ſit down and weep over you, than preach on, and direct you to what you intend not. The <hi>Ark of God,</hi> and the <hi>Idol of Philiſthia,</hi> could not ſtand upon the ſame Altar. Neither can a Choice of <hi>God</hi>'s Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and the <hi>World</hi>'s, conſiſt in the ſame Heart. Heaven and Earth be not ſuch Equals, as that they ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, and agree to take equal Shares in our Affections. So that if any thing be done to purpoſe, to this Effect muſt be your Language: <hi>What have I to do any more with Idols? I do renounce them; with full purpoſe applying my ſelf to ſeek God's Acquaintance. I am on and off no longer now, but fixed. I ſee the Neceſſity, and ceaſe from the Impertinence of plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Difficulty. Let it coſt me right Hand, and right Eye; they ſhall go, if need be! I will not give over ſeeking this Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, though I die.</hi> No Man comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God's Acquaintance and Favour, till he is made thus <hi>willing in the Day of his Power!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:39190:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Hope the beſt; if your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Hands hang down, and Knees be fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet lift them up; Hope even againſt Hope, that, as much as you have provoked Him to Vengeance, God will, now, bring you to his Acquaintance.</hi> That, now he has <hi>given you to Will,</hi> he will alſo <hi>ſtrengthen you to Do,</hi> all that is neceſſary. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you much, with the afflictive Thoughts of your long Enmity unto Him. But, join not with the Tempter, againſt your ſelf and your ſo gracious Father. Do not tell your ſelves, that you ſhall never ſee any Good come of your good Purpoſes. That, they are in vain; and 'tis not likely, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſo Holy, ſhould ever be propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated to you, or you be made ſutable or acceptable to Him. But, that, as when He was willing, you would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled; ſo, now that you are willing, he will not incline to Friendſhip. Give him not ſo inſolently the Lie, with your Mouth or Hearts; and abhor the thought of <hi>his being unreconcilably angred,</hi> or, <hi>your being unalterably wicked.</hi> Tell your ſelves the truth; He is not <hi>implacable</hi> by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39190:34"/>the Oblation of his Son, nor are you <hi>unreformable</hi> by the Power of his Spirit. A Spirit, which he hath promiſed <hi>to give unto them that ask;</hi> as you are now reſolved to do, and that without ceaſing. No Man came ever into God's Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without this Hope and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; that, <hi>There is Forgiveneſs with him!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>Seek as for Silver; ſearch as for hid Treaſure, for the ſound Knowledg of your Righteouſneſs, your Strength, and your Steps.</hi> Hope, is a Spring of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and unto nothing more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than this, can it move you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Righteouſneſs, is Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> His Righteouſneſs, is the true and only, that ſatisfieth for Iniquity, and meriteth Mercy. The great Apoſtle proteſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Truſt in any beſide. Though, after his Converſion, he was a ſort of incarnate Angel, he dared to plead no other Righteouſneſs at God's Tribunal. Knowing all other Garments to have both <hi>Defects and Defilement,</hi> he declareth <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God's Son,</hi> to be <hi>the Robe of his Salvation,</hi> Phil. 3.7, 8, 9.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39190:34"/>Natural Conſcience, as ſoon as it's awake, cries out, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> But, as ſoon as its Eyes are touched with the Eye-ſalve of the Goſpel, it ſees, that, <hi>It can never be ſaved by what it will ever be able to do! When we have done all, we are unprofitable Servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Strength is the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> We have no more Juſtifying Righteouſneſs than we receive from Chriſt; nor any more ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Righteouſneſs than we receive from the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>The Spirit helpeth our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</hi> Look over the Goſpel, you will find him entituled to all. To all <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> as the Worker of them; to all <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> as the Aſſiſter in them. He it is, that works all Good in us; and by whom we are acted when we do what is Good. The Body is not more dead and unactive without the Soul, than the beſt Soul is without the Holy Spirit. <hi>Without him we can do nothing. No Man can call Jeſus Lord but by the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Steps (thro Chriſt, and by the Holy Ghoſt) to God's Acquaintance,</hi> are theſe. <hi>e.gr. Painful Senſe of your want of it;</hi> for, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that mourn. <hi>Longing deſire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it;</hi> for, Bleſſed are they that hunger
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39190:35"/>and thirſt. <hi>Humble Acknowledgment of your Weakneſs, and diſability to raiſe your ſelves to it;</hi> for, Bleſſed are the poor in Spirit. <hi>Like acknowledgment of your being unworthy that God ſhould raiſe you up;</hi> for, we are Ungodly, as well as without Strength, and leſs than the leaſt of God's Mercies. <hi>Faith of God's Power and Readineſs, in his Goſpel-way, to raiſe you up to it;</hi> for, He that cometh to God, muſt believe that he is, and is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of them that ſeek him. <hi>Faith of his Willingneſs, with his Acquaintance, freely to give you all things;</hi> for, ſo is his Promiſe, No good Thing will he withhold from the Upright. Laſtly, <hi>Humble Boldneſs in the Faith aforeſaid, to truſt and ſerve Him;</hi> for, ſo is the Divine Preſcription, Let us come boldly to the Throne of Grace. When you are come boldly thither, you muſt lay down the Body before you can get higher: For, it is ſo high, that the next Step is Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſaith one of Note in the Church. Theſe things, <hi>Bind on your Fingers, write on the Table of your Hearts!</hi> Praying inceſſantly, that by the Holy Spirit's ſtrengthning Power, you may ever take theſe Steps; and through Chriſt's me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory Righteouſneſs, be accepted in them.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39190:35"/>For this, keep you <hi>praying with all Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Sanctify a Faſt; ſome Time ſet apart, and go Vow unto the Lord to be his; ſolemnly give your ſelves unto him; preſent your ſelves living Sacrifices.</hi> With what ſolemnity is the <hi>Nuptial Bond</hi> entred, every where in the World? With what Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is a <hi>Coronation-Oath</hi> taken? Yet, what is the <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of the one, or the <hi>Honour</hi> of the other, to that of the <hi>Covenant of Grace?</hi> The Covenant, by which <hi>our Maker</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>our Husband?</hi> And, we are made <hi>Princes!</hi> How congruous is it, that the Day of our entring it, ſhould be kept with greateſt Solemnity, and ſignalized as <hi>a Day never to be forgotten!</hi> That, every one joined to God therein, ſhould all Days of his Life moſt joyfully commemorate it; ſaying, <hi>This is the Day whereon I renewed my Baptiſmal Covenant! Was married to my God, was crowned with the Honour of his near Acquaintance, and enriched with all Peace and Good! Thanks be to God on every Remembrance!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this Renewal of our Baptiſmal Vow is needful; and the Repetition of it, upon all proper Occaſions, none can que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39190:36"/>The <hi>Examples</hi> that commend it, and the <hi>Reaſons</hi> that enforce it, are well known. I ſay but this; God, though no Debtor at all to us, pleaſeth by Promiſes of Free Grace, in effect, to become one. Men love to have their Favours free; are impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of being fettered by Promiſes unto their <hi>Alms-fokls;</hi> and do reſerve to themſelves a Power of revoking their Charity at Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But, <hi>God is Love;</hi> and ſuch, that, tho all his <hi>Bleſſings</hi> be <hi>Gifts,</hi> he condeſcends to be engaged for the conferring of them; and allows them in a Senſe to have the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Debts.</hi> In ſhort; tho <hi>his Word is eſtabliſhed in Heaven;</hi> and with Him <hi>is no ſhadow of turning;</hi> yet his <hi>Mercy</hi> is ſecured by <hi>Covenant,</hi> and his <hi>Covenant</hi> ſecured by <hi>Oath.</hi> Even, the higheſt Oath, <hi>by his Life,</hi> and <hi>by his Holineſs.</hi> What then? Shall we, who are <hi>Debtors,</hi> the deepeſt; we, whoſe <hi>Gifts</hi> unto Him, all are <hi>Debts,</hi> and ten thouſand times <hi>leſs than our Debts;</hi> We, whoſe Hearts are <hi>falſe,</hi> and need be fix'd and faſtned; <hi>ſluggiſh</hi> alſo, and need to be quickned; ſhall we think much to be bound in Vows? Or, ſhall we dare to truſt our Treacherous Spirits without them? What Bands and Cords can be too many
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39190:36"/>for us! Surely it ſtands us upon, by theſe Vows, as ſo many <hi>Girdles of Truth,</hi> to bind on us <hi>the whole Armour of God;</hi> if, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off our <hi>old Agreement with Hell,</hi> we would enter and maintain <hi>Acquaintance with God!</hi> And thus doth every Penitent, who attends the Overture made by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; <hi>Let him take hold of my Strength; that he may make Peace with me, and he ſhall make Peace with me,</hi> Iſa. 27.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>Pay your Vows; prove what is the good, and acceptable, and perfect Will of God; be not content to keep you from preſumptuous Sins, unleſs the Words of your Mouth, and the Meditations of your Heart be acceptable in the ſight of God!</hi> Vows turn to a ſad Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, unleſs, being bound, you do thus Obey. Taking heed of <hi>Gnats,</hi> as well as of <hi>Camels;</hi> of <hi>Moats,</hi> as well as of <hi>Beams.</hi> Ambitious to <hi>pleaſe,</hi> to <hi>well-pleaſe,</hi> yea and to <hi>beſt-pleaſe</hi> God. Your <hi>Minds</hi> proving what doth do ſo, by ſtudying it out; your <hi>Wills,</hi> by embracing it; and your <hi>active Powers,</hi> by practiſing it. Practiſing it to the beſt of your <hi>Light,</hi> and to the utmoſt of your <hi>Strength;</hi> with all your <hi>Mind,</hi> and with all your <hi>Soul.</hi> For, as fair as the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39190:37"/>Tree of Knowledg is to look on, the Tree of Life is the beſt to feed on. And if pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Holineſs be not the Life of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, our Judg will abominate our Heads of Gold upon Feet of Clay. Follow you therefore the Apoſtle's Rule, (too hot for Hypocrites to hold;) <hi>Whatſoever things are True, are Honeſt, are Juſt, are Pure, are Lovely, are of good Report; if there be any Vertue, (i. e.</hi> any more vertuous than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) <hi>if there be any Praiſe, (i. e.</hi> more praiſe-worthy than others) <hi>Think on theſe things, theſe things do!</hi> It is true, and a moſt comforting Truth; that, in our weak and tempted State. <hi>God will not reckon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sin a Revolt!</hi> That which we <hi>diſallow and deplore,</hi> He will not vindictively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. As Amity between Princes is not broken by what is done <hi>by Pirats,</hi> if they are not countenanced <hi>by ſupream Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders;</hi> ſo, our Acquaintance with God is not broke, by every inordinacy of <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Appetite,</hi> if it be not indulged by the <hi>ſuperior Faculties.</hi> If the <hi>Will</hi> doth the mean time conſent that <hi>the Law is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Juſt, and Good,</hi> and calls to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> for Arguments againſt the breach of it; if the <hi>Mind</hi> and the <hi>Heart</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:39190:37"/>do <hi>defy the Sin,</hi> the Sin doth not then break our Acquaintance. But otherwiſe; it worketh in our Souls a <hi>Dread and a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> of God. It maketh that we neither dare, nor deſire to approach him. And, cauſeth, on God's Part, a <hi>ſad Reſtraint,</hi> and <hi>ſuſpenſion of Grace and Peace,</hi> as to the uſual degree of Communication. Who knows not what <hi>David's</hi> Bones felt, for his Sin of this ſort? And, who is he, that hath not himſelf dearly ſmarted for it? Or, who, that knows God, wonders at it? He will be <hi>Juſt</hi> as well as <hi>Merciful</hi> in his deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his own Children. And will make them to know, that he can endure no Sin in them, that they are able to endure in themſelves! Sin againſt Knowledg, being Death to Acquaintance! Which, if we would maintain effectually to our Peace, we muſt walk as we are taught by Divine Grace; <hi>denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and worldly Luſts; i. e.</hi> refuſing <hi>aſſent</hi> to their lying <hi>Suggeſtions</hi> of Pleaſure and Profit; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing <hi>Conſent</hi> unto their importunate <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations.</hi> Behaving our ſelves <hi>ſoberly,</hi> in the Duties of our perſonal Capacity; <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly,</hi> in relative Duties to Men; and <hi>Godly,</hi> in the Duties of immediate Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39190:38"/>with God. Then may we, in Peace, <hi>Look for the bleſſed Hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="eulogy">
               <p>Thus <hi>Lived,</hi> and for this <hi>looked</hi> the rare Chriſtian, whoſe Deceaſe hath occaſioned this Diſcourſe. <hi>A Chriſtian much more in Truth than in Appearance.</hi> One of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, that bare <hi>few Leaves</hi> with much <hi>Fruit.</hi> Soveraign Grace moſt richly adorned her Perſon; but my Skill ſhall not be ſtrained <hi>to garniſh her Tomb.</hi> Only, as in the Place of a laſt Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I add thus much, not as <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> but as <hi>Sermon.</hi> Of the <hi>Honour of her Parentage,</hi> of the <hi>Beauty of her Perſon,</hi> and <hi>other common Gifts,</hi> which do not make known God's Love or Hatred; I ſay not any thing. <hi>Eccleſia, haec, tanquam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervacanea, dimittit;</hi> ſaith an Antient Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Though, in the World theſe do make great Figures, the Church takes them for no more than Cyphers. This only I exhort; <hi>The things which ſome of you have ſeen in her, more of you have Heard, and all of you ſhall Now-Hear, theſe things Seek, and theſe Do, and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39190:38"/>God of Peace ſhall be with you.</hi> A ſummary of them, as for ſome Years I have both <hi>Heard</hi> and <hi>Seen</hi> them, I give in few words; and in no more than theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</label> 
                  <hi>Extenſive</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Revealed as well as of Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; <hi>Intenſive,</hi> of Clear as well as of true Light; and <hi>Applicative,</hi> taking all that God ſaith as ſpoken to ones ſelf, as well as to others. This is what is wrought by <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> which God's Children have <hi>from the Holy One.</hi> This is the Wiſdom that is unto Salvation. This was eminently in Her of whom we ſpeak, a <hi>Guide</hi> unto Duty, and a <hi>Keeper</hi> therein; a <hi>Judg</hi> condemning for Neglect of Duty, and a <hi>Lictor,</hi> puniſhing for all done amiſs. Other Light, is but <hi>Ignis fatuus;</hi> other Knowledg, but <hi>Learned Ignorance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Holy Affections.</label> Holily <hi>Directed,</hi> by the Dictates of an informed Judgment; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily <hi>Set</hi> upon deſerving Objects; and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily <hi>Proportionated,</hi> according to their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Degrees of Goodneſs, and Deſerts. Theſe Affections, are our Souls Feet, and Wings; in Actions Natural, Civil, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39190:39"/>Religious, theſe are the things that move us. Inſomuch, that while theſe are Naught, we cannot do the leaſt Good. But, when theſe are Rectified, in the Goſpel Senſe we are <hi>Perfect,</hi> and <hi>throughly Furniſhed unto every good Work.</hi> The Father and the Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of Spirits, ſo regulated the Affections of this his Servant's Spirit; that, Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, if ſhe had any, would confeſs them to have bin ſet upon <hi>the One thing neceſſary!</hi> and ſo ſet, as hath been ſaid!</p>
               <p>
                  <label>True Diligence.</label> Such as ſtirs <hi>Promptly,</hi> as Flames do Aſcend; <hi>Earneſtly,</hi> as for Life, with all Violence and with both Hands; and <hi>Inceſſantly,</hi> as Waters flow from Fountains. Such was her Induſtry in Sacred Affairs. Unto them, her <hi>Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> prevented Human Perſwaſion; and in them ſhe appeared to be none of that ſad Multitude who ſo <hi>Pray</hi> as though they cared not whether they ſped; and ſo <hi>Hear God's Word,</hi> as though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired nothing leſs than to Profit. Who ever ſaw her in <hi>Prayer,</hi> but moſt Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent? in <hi>Hearing,</hi> but moſt fixedly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? A moſt uſeful <hi>Pattern</hi> to the Congregation wherein ſhe Worſhipped.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39190:39"/>Her <hi>Perſeverance</hi> in this, was unfainting to the laſt; her <hi>Spirit was Willing, when her Fleſh was Weak.</hi> The very Day before her Aſcenſion, how eagerly did ſhe <hi>Point,</hi> when ſhe could not <hi>ſpeak;</hi> and make <hi>Signs</hi> when ſhe could utter no <hi>Words,</hi> to have Holy Prayer put up? There was no extinction of the Fire upon her Altar; it Aſcended with Her.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Exemplary Patience.</label> A <hi>Silently-ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one,</hi> as that of <hi>David,</hi> who was Dumb, becauſe it was God who ſmote him; a <hi>Thankfully-Accepting one,</hi> as that of <hi>Job,</hi> who Bleſſed God <hi>Taking away</hi> good things, as well as <hi>Giving</hi> of them; and a <hi>Chearfully-Receiving one,</hi> as that of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s, who Gloried, or <hi>Rejoiced in Tribulations!</hi> In all her <hi>Moanings,</hi> throughout her long Sickneſs, I heard no <hi>Murmuring!</hi> But a perpetual Acknowledgment of the Divine Goodneſs, in Mitigating her Pains, and Moderating her Sorrows!</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Profound Thankfulneſs.</label> 
                  <hi>Cordial,</hi> when the Heart is by Gifts made an Oblation to the Giver; <hi>Oral,</hi> when the Mouth is made a Trumpet of his Goodneſs; <hi>Practical,</hi> when
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39190:40"/>it's made the Buſineſs of our whole Life, to give him the Glory of his Bounty. This, which is the Soul of all Religion, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuoſly the Exerciſe and Delight of her Religious Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Godlineſs.</label> The higheſt and moſt ſolemn Reſpects toward God, as the <hi>Firſt Cauſe,</hi> aſcribing all Good unto Him, and Truſting Him for all; as the <hi>Chiefeſt Good,</hi> Reverencing of Him and Delighting in Him; as the <hi>Supream Power,</hi> ſubjecting us to his Authority, and yielding Obedience to his Laws; as the <hi>Laſt End,</hi> Glorifying Him in all Things, and above all Things! O happy Days, when there ſhall be found many <hi>ſuch manner of Perſons, for all holy Converſation and Godlineſs!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Chriſtian Charity.</label> Of <hi>Pity,</hi> towards God's Enemies; of <hi>Pardon,</hi> towards our own Enemies; of <hi>Complacence</hi> in good Men; of <hi>Benevolence</hi> to all Men. This was her <hi>Sweet</hi> and <hi>Gentle</hi> Temper, her <hi>Kind</hi> and <hi>Meek</hi> Spirit! A Temper moſt <hi>Delightful</hi> to her ſelf, moſt <hi>Beneficial</hi> to all about her, moſt <hi>Like unto God,</hi> and moſt <hi>Acceptable</hi> to Him!</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:39190:40"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Excellent and regular Moderation.</label> Such Government of the Affections, as keepeth from being <hi>brought under the Power of any;</hi> either in the <hi>Purſuit</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of things Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. That, wherein the <hi>deſiring Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite,</hi> is, with Sobriety and Temperance, reſtrain'd from inordinate Pleaſure; and the <hi>angry Appetite,</hi> is, with Fortitude and Patience bridled from unrighteous Wrath. That, whereby we are enfranchiſed from Captivity unto Senſe, and have Spiritual Dominion eſtabliſhed over our Brutiſh part. That, whereby we are <hi>Crucified to the World, and the World is Crucified to us,</hi> as the Sacred Writer ſpeaks; <hi>q. d.</hi> the Love and Fear of the World is regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in us; ſo that it can no more ſeduce or Terrify us. That, through which Chriſtian Souldiers, get the Maſtery over the bloody Conſpirators; this <hi>World</hi> (their Tempter) and the <hi>Body</hi> (their Traitor.) Surrounded with Riches and Honours, and in a Proſperity, full of Temptations, as <hi>Nilus</hi> of <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> this Moderation of her's, was well known! In our lower ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of fewer Blandiſhments and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, may our like <hi>Moderation be known unto all Men!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:39190:41"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Hope to the End.</label> Aſſent to the Truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt; Reliance upon the Goodneſs of God reconciled by Him; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the promiſed incorruptible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; and all three maintained unto Death. Of the many Months, whereof I was not abſent from her Chamber many Days, never could I diſcern her <hi>Hope to be departed.</hi> Nor ever heard her complain, that it was <hi>Departed.</hi> Indeed, the beſt Hope ſometime lieth Proſtrate; <hi>Abraham,</hi> was not always <hi>Abraham.</hi> When it was worſt with her, it was no worſe than with <hi>Job,</hi> in whoſe words ſhe expreſs'd it; <hi>Tho He Slay me, I will Truſt in Him! He knows the Way that I have Choſen!</hi> It's not every <hi>dark-Cloud,</hi> that maketh <hi>Night;</hi> nor every <hi>ſad-Doubt and Fear,</hi> that is to be named <hi>Deſpair.</hi> This therefore I teſtify; I have oft ſeen her <hi>Troubled,</hi> but not once <hi>Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> often <hi>Perplexed,</hi> but not once <hi>in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair!</hi> May all that hear this, have ſo <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built Hope in their Death!</hi> Then, how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly ſoever the old Serpent may <hi>Hiſs,</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally it ſhall not <hi>Sting!</hi> Whereof, I am much the more confident, becauſe of that wherein ſhe peculiarly excelled,</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:39190:41"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Conſpicuous Humility.</label> A <hi>Mind,</hi> of low thoughts of her Self; a <hi>Will,</hi> of no deſire to be thought more highly of than is meet; a <hi>Language</hi> and <hi>Behaviour</hi> convincingly ſhowing both. No, Obſervation, or Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of mine, hath given me to know the Saint, wherein Humility had its more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Work. But, hereof ſo much is <hi>known,</hi> that no more ſhall be <hi>told.</hi> This only is ſuggeſted; it's nothing but Acquaintance with God, that can <hi>truly Humble</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> Men and Augels. This it is that mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Seraphims</hi> to <hi>cover their Wings, Feet, and Faces;</hi> and to feel a <hi>fulneſs of Joy and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore</hi> in ſo doing. Which, it is moſt reaſonable to believe, ſhe is now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying with them. Inſomuch, that I am bold thus to conclude; <hi>I would to God that not only I, but alſo all that hear me this Day, were both almoſt and altogether ſuch, as it is meet to believe this great Lover of her God was; except but her Infirmities,</hi> which ſhe ever bewailed, and <hi>Tribulations,</hi> through which ſhe Paſſed into the Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom! <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
